<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY PRODUCT "Xenta OS">
<!ENTITY MINTVERSION "2.0 LTS">
<!ENTITY BOOKID "User_Guide">
<!ENTITY YEAR "2019">
<!ENTITY HOLDER "Xenta OS">
<!ENTITY EDITION "Xfce">
]>
<chapter id="installation">
	<title>Cara Menginstall Xenta OS</title>
	 <para>
		Anda dapat mengunduh sistem operasi Xenta OS secara gratis di http://www.xentaos.com/. Filenya berupa ISO yang harus Anda burn ke DVD kosong atau melakukan bootable ke flashdisk.<footnote>
		<para>
			Dan juga dapat dengan cara melakukan bootable ISO ke stik USB atau perangkat memori lain dan mem-boot dari situ, atau juga mem-bootable dari ISO ke hard drive, pilihan ini lebih maju dan metode yang disajikan di sini direkomendasikan. Untuk bantuan dan informasi lebih lanjut dengan metode alternatif menginstal dan menjalankan Xenta OS, silakan kunjungi forum.
		</para>
		</footnote>. LiveDVD kemudian dapat berjalan dengan sistem operasi yang terinstal di dalamnya dan berfungsi penuh yang dapat Anda coba tanpa mempengaruhi PC Anda. Dalam istilah awam, ketika Anda menjalankan Xenta OS pada DVD/FD dan memasukkannya ke komputer Anda, Anda dapat mencobanya tanpa perlu khawatir data Anda terganggu.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Jika Anda menyukai apa yang Anda lihat saat menjalankan liveDVD, Anda dapat memutuskan untuk menginstal sistem operasi Xenta OS ke hard drive Anda. Semua alat yang diperlukan (alat partisi dan instalasi) ada di DVD.
	</para>
	 <sect1 id="download-iso"> <title>Unduh ISO Xenta OS</title>
	 <para>
		Untuk mengunduh sistem operasi Xenta OS, silahkan kunjungi halaman unduhan Xenta OS di <ulink url="http://www.xentaos.org/p/download.html">http://www.xentaos.org/p/download.html</ulink> dan pilih edisi yang Anda minati.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Dari halaman ini, Anda dapat menemukan:
	</para>
	 <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				an MD5 signature
			</para>
		</listitem>
		 <listitem>
			<para>
				tautan torrent
			</para>
		</listitem>
		 <listitem>
			<para>
				daftar mirror unduhan
			</para>
		</listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
	 <para>
		File yang perlu Anda unduh adalah file ISO. Ada dua cara untuk mengunduh file ini, yang pertama dengan torrent (protokol Peer to Peer) atau melalui mirror download (protokol HTTP atau FTP). Setelah unduhan Anda selesai, Anda dapat memastikan file ISO Anda tidak rusak dengan memeriksa signature with the MD5.
	</para>
	 <note>
		<para>
			Jika Anda tidak memiliki koneksi internet, atau jika akses internet Anda terlalu lambat, Anda dapat memesan DVD di <ulink url="http://www.xentaos.org/p/store.html">http://www.xentaos.org/p/store.html</ulink>.
		</para>
	</note>
	 <sect2> <title>Melalui torrent</title>
	 <para>
		Torrent adalah protokol Peer to Peer (P2P). Pada dasarnya, alih-alih mengunduh dari lokasi pusat, torrent memungkinkan Anda mengunduh file ISO di bagian-bagian dari orang yang berbeda di Internet.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Semakin banyak orang yang mengunduh file ISO, semakin cepat kecepatan unduhannya. Ini adalah cara yang disukai dan direkomendasikan untuk mengunduh Xenta OS.
	</para>
	 <sect3> <title>Instal klien Torrent</title>
	 <para>
		Anda memerlukan perangkat lunak yang disebut "klien torrent" untuk mengunduh file melalui torrent.
	</para>
	 <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Jika Anda menjalankan Xenta OS, Anda sudah menginstal klien torrent.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		 <listitem>
			<para>
				Jika Anda menjalankan distribusi Linux lain, Anda dapat menginstal aplikasi "Transmission".
			</para>
		</listitem>
		 <listitem>
			<para>
				Jika Anda menggunakan Windows, Anda dapat menggunakan μTorrent.
			</para>
		</listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
	 </sect3> <sect3> <title>Unduh File Torrent</title>
	 <para>
		Langkah selanjutnya adalah mengakses tautan torrent dari situs web Xenta OS dan mengunduh file .torrent. File ini sangat kecil. Setelah mengunduhnya, Anda harus membukanya dengan klien torrent Anda.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Klien torrent mungkin akan bertanya kepada Anda di mana Anda ingin menyimpan file ISO. Pilih tujuan dan kemudian tunggu unduhannya selesai.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Untuk informasi lebih lanjut tentang protokol torrent, kunjungi <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BitTorrent">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BitTorrent</ulink>.
	</para>
	 </sect3> </sect2> <sect2> <title>Melalui Unduhan Langsung</title>
	 <para>
		Jika Anda tidak bisa, atau tidak memilih untuk menggunakan protokol torrent, maka lihatlah daftar mirror unduhan dan pilih salah satunya. Mereka akan memberikan tautan ke file ISO itu sendiri yang dapat Anda klik untuk mulai mengunduh.
	</para>
	 </sect2> </sect1> <sect1> <title>Silahkan Baca Catatan Rilis</title>
	 <para>
		Unduhan Anda mungkin akan bertahan setidaknya satu jam, jadi sekarang adalah waktu yang tepat bagi Anda untuk mengenal fitur-fitur baru yang datang dengan rilis yang sedang Anda unduh.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Catatan rilis ditampilkan di halaman web Xenta OS dan menjawab pertanyaan berikut:
	</para>
	 <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Apa saja fitur baru yang diberikan dalam rilis ini?
			</para>
		</listitem>
		 <listitem>
			<para>
				Apa masalah yang diketahui dari rilis ini?
			</para>
		</listitem>
		 <listitem>
			<para>
				Bagaimana cara mengupgrade OS Saya dari rilis sebelumnya?
			</para>
		</listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
	 <para>
		Catatan rilis juga berisi tangkapan layar dari rilis terbaru. Tentu saja, Anda dapat mencari tahu tentang sebagian besar fitur yang disorot dalam catatan rilis dengan hanya menggunakan sistem operasi, tetapi Anda mungkin kehilangan beberapa hal, jadi metode paling andal untuk membaca catatan rilis.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Catatan rilis untuk Xenta OS 1.3 LTS Arok tersedia di <ulink url="http://www.xentaos.org/2017/08/rilis-xenta-os-13-lts-arok-cinnamon.html">http://www.xentaos.org/2017/08/rilis-xenta-os-13-lts-arok-cinnamon.html</ulink>
	</para>
	 </sect1> <sect1> <title>Cek MD5</title>
	 <para>
		Jika Anda telah membaca catatan rilis, dan Anda tidak sabar untuk bermain dengan fitur baru atau mencoba Xenta OS, dan unduhan Anda baru saja selesai dengan sukses. Anda siap burn to DVD dan menjalankannya ... tapi hei! Tunggu sebentar!
	</para>
	 <para>
		Jika DVD itu rusak, Anda akan menjumpai bug aneh dan akan kesulitan menemukan bantuan. Dua alasan paling umum mengapa DVD rusak adalah:
	</para>
	 <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				An issue with the download causing problems in your ISO file
			</para>
		</listitem>
		 <listitem>
			<para>
				An error during the burn process that alters the contents of your burned liveDVD
			</para>
		</listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
	 <para>
		The MD5 signature, which is present on the download page, provides a quick way for you to make sure that your ISO file is exactly like it should be. So, let’s check the ISO file you just downloaded before we burn it and save ourselves from a lot of potential problems.
	</para>
	 <para>
		If you run any version of Linux you probably already have the md5sum program installed. Open a terminal and “cd” to the directory where your ISO file is (for instance, if “linuxmint.iso” is on the Desktop), open a terminal and type:
	</para>
	 
<screen>
                <command>cd ~/Desktop</command>
                <command>md5sum <replaceable>myfile.iso</replaceable></command>
</screen>
	 <para>
		This command should output a series of numbers and letters which comprise the MD5 sum, or signature, of your ISO file. By design, any small change to the ISO file will cause this signature to be significantly different, allowing us to verify that the file is exactly as it should be.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Compare that signature with the one on the download page of the Xenta OS website. If the two signatures are the same, then you know your ISO file is exactly the same as the original and you can now get ready to burn it on DVD.
	</para>
	 <note>
		<para>
			If you happen to run Windows, chances are you don’t have md5sum installed. You can get it from here: <ulink url="http://www.etree.org/md5com.html">http://www.etree.org/md5com.html</ulink>
		</para>
		 <para>
			Place the ISO file and the md5sum.exe in the same place (let’s say in C:\) and run “cmd.exe”. In the command line environment, type the following commands:
		</para>
		 
<screen>
                <command>C:</command>
                <command>cd \</command>
                <command>md5sum <replaceable>myfile.iso</replaceable></command>
</screen>
		 <para>
			Then compare the signature to the one present on the website.
		</para>

	</note>
	 </sect1> <sect1> <title>Burn the ISO to DVD</title>
	 <para>
		Now that you have checked the ISO file with MD5, you are ready to burn it to a DVD.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Get a blank DVD-R (a DVD-RW should work as well, but this type of media is known to have compatibility issues) and your favorite marker and label the DVD. Although labeling your DVDs sounds trivial, you should be sure to do so, as you can easily end up with 20 unlabeled and unidentifiable discs on your desk. :)
	</para>
	 <para>
		Insert the blank DVD-R in the drive and get ready to burn the ISO.
	</para>
	 <para>
		If you’re running Linux with Cinnamon right-click on the ISO file and select: open with: Brasero, choose “Burn image” and follow the steps given there.
	</para>
	 <para>
		If you’re running Linux with KDE, launch K3B and in the “Tools” menu choose “Write ISO Image”.
	</para>
	 <para>
		If you’re running Windows you can use a program like InfraRecorder.
	</para>
	 <note>
		<para>
			Make sure to burn the ISO image to disk, and not to write the ISO file to the disk. A very common mistake, especially for people using Nero, is to actually burn the ISO file on the disk as a data file. The ISO file is an image of a disk so it needs to be burnt not as a file which will appear on the disk, but as an ISO image which will be decompressed and whose content will be burnt onto the disc. After burning the DVD you shouldn't see the ISO file within the disc, but rather folders like “casper” or “isolinux”. Most burning software has a special option for this.
		</para>
	</note>
	 </sect1> <sect1> <title>Boot the LiveDVD</title>
	 <para>
		Place the DVD in the drive and restart the computer. You should now see the following screen:
	</para>
	 <figure id="installation-isolinux">
		<title>The boot screen</title>
		 <screenshot> <mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/isolinux.png" format="PNG" width="100%" />
			</imageobject>

		</mediaobject>
		 </screenshot>
	</figure>
	 <note>
		<para>
			If you don’t see this screen and your PC boots as usual it’s probably because your BIOS is not set to boot on DVD. Restart the computer and press F1, F2, Delete, or Escape (or whatever key lets you enter the BIOS configuration) and change your BIOS settings to tell your computer to boot from its DVD drive.
		</para>
	</note>
	 </sect1> <sect1> <title>Install Xenta OS on your hard drive</title>
	 <para>
		From the first screen choose the default <guilabel>Start Xenta OS</guilabel> option and press Enter. After a little while the live system should be ready and you should see the desktop.
	</para>
	 <para>
		At this stage Xenta OS is not installed on your computer, it’s simply running from the DVD. The system you have in front of you is, however, almost exactly the same as the one you will have on your computer after the installation is finished.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Have fun with it and see if you like it. Bear in mind that when running from the DVD, Xenta OS runs significantly slower than it does when it is installed on a hard drive, since it has to read data from the DVD drive, which is a slower medium than the hard drive.
	</para>
	 <para>
		When you are ready, double-click on the <guilabel>Install Xenta OS</guilabel> icon located on the desktop. The Installer appears:
	</para>
	 <figure id="installation-languages">
		<title>The language selection screen</title>
		 <screenshot> <mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/installation_languages.png" format="PNG" width="100%" />
			</imageobject>

		</mediaobject>
		 </screenshot>
	</figure>
	 <para>
		If you haven’t read the release notes yet, and you have an Internet connection, then this an ideal opportunity to review them; simply click on the underlined link. It is highly recommended that users read the release notes prior to installation in order to advise themselves of new features, as well as any issues that might affect their particular hardware configuration.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Select your language and press the <guibutton>Continue</guibutton> button.
	</para>
	 <figure id="installation-warning">
		<title>Checking that everything is fine...</title>
		 <screenshot> <mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/installation_warning.png" format="PNG" width="100%" />
			</imageobject>

		</mediaobject>
		 </screenshot>
	</figure>
	 <para>
		In the next screen, make sure you're connected to a power source (if you're using a laptop), the Internet and that you have the recommended amount of disk space. Then press the <guibutton>Continue</guibutton> button.
	</para>
	 <figure id="installation-type">
		<title>Choosing an installation type</title>
		 <screenshot> <mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/installation_type.png" format="PNG" width="100%" />
			</imageobject>

		</mediaobject>
		 </screenshot>
	</figure>
	 <para>
		In the next screen you can assign your entire hard drive to Xenta OS or install it alongside other operating systems. Alternatively, you can also define and assign the partitions manually.
	</para>
	 <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				If you choose to use the entire disk, its content will be erased and Xenta OS will be installed as the only operating system on your computer.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		 <listitem>
			<para>
				If you choose to install it alongside other operating systems, the installer will use the free space available on other partitions to create a new one for Xenta OS. You will be asked how much space you want to allocate to it. The installer will then shrink a partition and take care of everything for you. Post-installation your computer will have a boot screen from which you'll be able to boot all your operating systems.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		 <listitem>
			<para>
				If you choose to specify partitions manually, a partition editor will appear, giving you full control over the partitioning of your hard drive. This is recommended only to advanced users who understand how partitioning works under Linux. Note that Xenta OS requires a partition of at least 6GB and that the recommended size for a swap partition is 1.5 times the amount of RAM available on the computer.
			</para>
		</listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
	 <figure id="installation-drive">
		<title>The installation summary screen</title>
		 <screenshot> <mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/installation_drive.png" format="PNG" width="100%" />
			</imageobject>

		</mediaobject>
		 </screenshot>
	</figure>
	 <para>
		Choose the appropriate option and click on the <guibutton>Install Now</guibutton> button. At this stage, the installation is going on in the background and the installer asks you setup questions:
	</para>
	 <figure id="installation-timezone">
		<title>Choosing a timezone</title>
		 <screenshot> <mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/installation_timezone.png" format="PNG" width="100%" />
			</imageobject>

		</mediaobject>
		 </screenshot>
	</figure>
	 <para>
		Choose your location on the map by clicking on the city which is the nearest to you. The purpose of this step is to identify your time zone. Make sure the <guilabel>Current time</guilabel> appears correctly and click the <guibutton>Continue</guibutton> button.
	</para>
	 <note>
		<para>
			Sometimes the installer doesn't properly handle Summer/Winter time adjustments, so even by selecting the proper city you might see a difference of an hour or so with the correct time. Simply ignore this at this stage and remember to make sure that the time is correct after you reboot in your newly installed Xenta OS desktop.
		</para>
	</note>
	 <figure id="installation-keyboard">
		<title>Choosing a keyboard layout</title>
		 <screenshot> <mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/installation_keyboard.png" format="PNG" width="100%" />
			</imageobject>

		</mediaobject>
		 </screenshot>
	</figure>
	 <para>
		Select your keyboard layout. If you are not sure about exactly which layout matches the keyboard you have, click on the text field at the bottom of the screen and start typing with your keyboard. Make sure the keys you press match the characters that appear in the text field in order to ensure you have selected the right keyboard layout. Some layouts only differ with respect to accents, numbers and punctuation signs, so make sure to test these as well.
	</para>
	 <para>
		When you’re ready click the <guibutton>Continue</guibutton> button.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Enter your real name and a username and password. Every time you’ll use Xenta OS you’ll use your account with this username and password. Once Xenta OS is installed you’ll be able to define other accounts if other people are to use this computer.
	</para>
	 <para>
		Also give your computer a name. This name will be used by your computer on the network or in various places of the system. If you’ve never really thought about naming your computers, then now is the time. People commonly pick flower (dahlia, rose, tulip) or planet (mars, jupiter, pluto) names for the computers on their network. It’s entirely up to you what you want to use, but make sure to pick a name you like and that you will easily remember.
	</para>
	 <note>
		<para>
			Capital letters, spaces and special characters are not permitted in the username or in the name of the computer.
		</para>
	</note>
	 <para>
		If you're the only one using the computer and you want to bypass the login screen, check the option <guilabel>Log in automatically</guilabel>.
	</para>
	 <para>
		When you’re ready click on the <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> button.
	</para>
	 <figure id="installation-user">
		<title>The user settings screen</title>
		 <screenshot> <mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/installation_user.png" format="PNG" width="100%" />
			</imageobject>

		</mediaobject>
		 </screenshot>
	</figure>
	 <para>
		The installer might detect other operating systems on your computer and ask you if you want to migrate some personal information. Typically this allows you to migrate bookmarks, contacts, favorites and other sorts of personal information from other operating systems installed on your hard disk drive into the newly installed Xenta OS. When you’re ready click on the <guibutton>Continue</guibutton> button.
	</para>
	 <figure id="installation-ongoing">
		<title>The installation usually takes between 10 and 15 minutes</title>
		 <screenshot> <mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/installation_ongoing.png" format="PNG" width="100%" />
			</imageobject>

		</mediaobject>
		 </screenshot>
	</figure>
	 <note>
		<para>
			The installer will download packages from the Internet to support the language you’ve selected. Your computer needs to be connected to the Internet for this to work. Otherwise just <guibutton>skip</guibutton> that step and you’ll be able to add support for your language after the installation is finished and you’ve rebooted into your new system.
		</para>
	</note>
	 <para>
		Once the installation is done click the <guibutton>Restart Now</guibutton> button and the liveDVD or LiveUSB environment will shut down.
	</para>
	 <para>
		When prompted, remove the DVD from the drive or remove the USB and press Enter. Your PC is now ready to boot Xenta OS from the hard drive.
	</para>
	 </sect1> <sect1> <title>Reboot the computer</title>
	 <para>
		Upon reboot, if you have more than one operating system installed, you should see a boot menu. Once Xenta OS is finished loading you should see a new screen inviting you to enter your username and password. This screen is the “MDM Login Manager” and is commonly called “MDM”. Enter the password you chose during the installation.
	</para>
	 <note>
		<para>
			By default, your “root” password is the same as the password you chose during the installation. If you do not know what this means, then don't worry about it.
		</para>
	</note>
	 </sect1>
</chapter>

